Ouch, that hurts!
很痛耶
Get off already!
放開我啦
Run!
快跑
Honestly…
老實說…
Kona is amazing!
小奈太棒了
You're so good at drawing.
你好會畫畫喔
I bet Tokio wouldn't like that.
時男知道了一定會很不開心
I wonder how Tokio is doing.
不曉得時男現在過得怎樣
Yeah…
對呀
I heard Kona is communicating with Tokio.
聽說小奈會和時男保持聯絡
It hurts, it hurts, it hurts!
好痛…好痛
It's okay, keep going.
沒事的，繼續用力
It hurts so much!
真的很痛
I'm dying! I'm dying!
我快死了，我快死了
-You can do it. -It hurts! I'm dying! I'm going to die!
-你可以的 -很痛，我快死了，我真的快死了
Kona!
小奈
Tokio.
時男
The baby will be born.
孩子快出生了
Hey.
喂
-Morning. -Don't climb on the car. You'll dent it.
-早安 -別爬到車頂，你會壓壞它
You've climbed up here plenty.
妳明明就爬上來過很多次
It's my car, so I can do what I want.
那是我的車，我想怎樣就怎樣
It's our car, by the way.
應該是我們的車才對
Wrong, it's mine.
錯，是我的
KIRUKO-NINE
（貴留子，九）
Kiruko-nine?
貴留子，九？
I was wondering what you were doing all morning.
我還正納悶你一整個早上都在做什麼
Pay attention, the character for Maru is like this.
看清楚，小丸的丸應該這樣寫
At least write it correctly.
至少要寫對
Oh, well.
算了
While we're at it, let's add Juichi's name.
說到這個，也把充一的名字加上去吧
Good idea.
好主意
KIRUKO MARU JUICHI
（貴留子，小丸，充一）
I know we've already written it,
我知道我們已經寫上去了
but I just realized Juichi's name makes it look like our 11th car.
但我突然發現充一的名字 會讓人以為這是我們的第11台車
So what if it does?
如果是又怎樣？
Trust is everything in my job.
我的工作最重要的一點是取信於人
I don't want people to think it's just some meaningless front.
我不希望大家以為這些字毫無意義
Well, at least the first Kirukomaru really existed.
至少貴留子小丸真的存在
You mean, the raft?
像救生艇那樣喔？
Wait, if you read Juichi's name as Roman numerals, it's Kirukomaru II!
對耶，如果把充一的名字看成是 羅馬數字，就會是貴留子小丸二號
So it makes perfect sense!
這就完全說得過去了
But then we're leaving Juichi out.
但充一就被排除在外了
Hey, stop nit-picking and give me directions.
別再雞蛋裡挑骨頭了，幫我指路
You're the nitpicker.
雞蛋裡挑骨頭的人明明是妳
TAKAHARA ACADEMY (IBARAKI FACILITY)
（高原學園） （茨城設施）
Right…
好的…
I don't get how you know the way with this information.
我不明白妳怎麼能夠 從這些資料看出該往哪裡走
If you wanna know about the old civilization, ask someone older.
如果你想了解舊時代的文明 就得問老一輩的人
So, tell me the status of the combatants.
告訴我戰鬥人員的狀況
It appears that after transportation, all eight awoke from suspended animation.
看來在運送過來之後 八隻都從休眠中甦醒了
The prototype of their Super-Beam is also ready.
他們的超級光線原型也準備好了
My next concern is the children's illness.
我接下來擔心的是孩子們的病情
Will the 5th year students fall ill too?
五年級生也會生病嗎？
Well, they could.
這個嘛…有可能
I'm not in a position to say that there's no possibility of that.
我沒有立場說不可能會生病
It's never straightforward with you, is it?
你這人從來不懂得直截了當，對吧？
It's a possibility.
有這種可能性
At present, we don't know the cause. We don't have a cure either.
目前我們還不知道原因，我們也沒有解藥
Just as I feared.
我怕的就是這個
We will just have to wager on it.
我們只能賭一把
Wager? Wager on what?
賭一把？賭什麼？
Tokio's child.
時男的孩子
The child of two children.
那兩個孩子的孩子
Not a child birthed by Mina, but a child of two children.
不是美娜生下的孩子 而是兩個孩子的孩子
This is far from what was planned.
這與我們的計畫差得十萬八千里
This is something else altogether!
這完全是另一回事
We will have to wager everything on Tokio's child.
我們得把一切下注在時男的孩子身上
You'll do it, won't you?
你會去做，對吧？
It's up to me to ensure with my own eyes
我得親眼目睹
that Heaven blooms in this utterly broken world.
天國在這個崩壞的世界裡蓬勃發展
But, unless the shackles of human mortality are broken,
但是，一定得打破人類壽命有限這個枷鎖
I cannot do so.
我才辦得到
Takahara Academy will break them.
高原學園將會打破這道枷鎖
B-But…
但是…
But for brain transplants, the container must be 15 years old.
但針對腦部移植，接受移植的人要滿15歲
They should be 13 at the very least. Otherwise it is impossible.
至少也要滿13歲，不然不可能成功
And I won't live another 13 years?
我無法再活13年嗎？
I see how it is.
我知道了啦
I'm just some dried up 80-year-old lady?
我只不過是個80多歲 快要入土的老太婆？
That level of agitation will only--
妳這麼激動只會…
Only what?
只會怎樣？
Shorten my life-span?
減短我的壽命？
Director!
園長
I lost my composure.
我失態了
I understand that my remaining years are limited.
我明白我的壽命已所剩無幾
You must have realized it
按照我的經驗看來
if your panic in the meeting earlier is anything to go by.
你先前在會議上驚慌失措 代表你早就看清這件事了
First, I'll become Miss Aoshima.
首先，我會成為青島小姐
Then I will wait patiently for the container to mature.
然後我會耐心等待接受移植的人漸漸成熟
I can withstand a second transplant if I wait that long, right?
如果我能等這麼久 我就可以承受第二次移植，對吧？
So that's why you increased Aoshima's access rights?
所以妳才會提高青島的權限？
Has Aoshima given her consent?
青島同意了嗎？
When you agree to become the assistant director,
當你同意成為助理園長時
you also agree to eventually become the director, right?
就等於你同意了最終會成為園長，對吧？
You expect this kind of absurdity to be permitted?
妳期待這種荒謬的事會獲得許可嗎？
Permitted? By who?
許可？被誰許可？
Permitted by law?
被法律許可嗎？
Or by international public opinion?
還是被國際輿論許可？
Those things are long gone.
那些東西早就不存在了
Or, could you mean…
還是…你的意思是…
God?
上帝？
You must know that, in the end,
你要知道，到最後
those are just different names to call the pressure to conform.
那些都是從眾壓力不同的代名詞而已
Aren't you at Takahara Academy to avoid being tied down by such things?
你來到高原學園不就是為了 避免被這種事情綁手綁腳嗎？
That is why we created Heaven.
所以我們才會創造了天國
There's already no turning back for us.
我們已經無路可退了
We either continue, or fail entirely.
要嘛繼續，要嘛徹底失敗
Make sure Tokio's child
確保時男能夠盡可能
is delivered as safely as possible.
平平安安地生下這個孩子
So cute.
好可愛
KIRUKOMARU II
（貴留子小丸二號）
Hey, are you okay?
你還好嗎？
So he can fight well and put up with the cold,
他很會打架，也能夠忍受寒冷
but is useless with car sickness.
但卻會暈車
I made some food, do you think you can eat some?
我煮了一些吃的，你有辦法吃嗎？
Food?
吃的？
What's this? Bread! Amazing.
這是什麼？麵包！太棒了
I found it in Kirukomaru II.
我在貴留子小丸二號上面發現的
LONG-LASTING BREAD
（長期保存麵包）
It expired seven years ago, so I toasted it over a fire, just in case.
七年前就過期了 以防萬一，我用火烤過了
It's tasty, this old civilization food.
舊文明時代的食物好好吃喔
I had a quick look around while you were sleeping,
你在睡覺的時候，我在附近繞了一圈
but this whole area has already been scavenged clean of stuff.
但這個區域早就被清空了
There isn't a single window in this house, let alone resources.
這棟房子連一扇窗戶都沒有 更別提資源了
You're right.
妳說的對
And also, there are pros and cons to having a car.
而且，有一輛車有利有弊
It's taking forever to get to our destination.
我們一輩子也到不了目的地吧
All because of some bumps we could easily get over on foot.
因為路面太崎嶇不平 用走的話早就過去了
ON THE BEACH: MANKIND'S FINAL DAYS - NEVIL SHUTE
（內佛舒特，《世界就是這樣結束的》）
Maru, turn off the light already.
小丸，把燈關了
Sorry, was it shining in your eyes?
抱歉，妳覺得很刺眼嗎？
No, not that.
不是啦
This house is so bare, anyone would see a light straightaway.
這棟房子裡空無一物 隨便一看都會碰到光線
We should be extra careful.
我們要特別提高警覺
Okay then.
好的
I shouldn't have napped earlier. Now I'm so awake…
我之前不該睡午覺的，現在一點都不睏
Wait, Sis!
等等，姊
She's already asleep.
她睡著了
Must be nice to fall asleep so fast.
能夠倒頭就睡的感覺一定很棒吧
Sis. I can see some smoke in the distance.
姊，我看到遠處有煙霧
Sure you're not dreaming?
你確定不是在做夢嗎？
There's no way you could see smoke far away at night.
這麼晚了，那麼遠的煙霧你看不到的啦
I'm not dreaming.
我不是在做夢
I didn't even go to sleep yet.
我根本就還沒睡著
-Oh, wow. You're right. -See?
-天啊，你沒說錯 -看吧？
If we can see that from this distance, there must be some light source below it.
如果我們在這麼遠的地方都看得到 那就表示下方一定有某種光源
So, let's get the map.
把地圖拿出來
And the compass.
還有指南針
It's definitely coming from the direction of the Ibaraki facility.
肯定是來自於茨城設施那個方向
Sh-Shall we go over there?
我們該過去看看嗎？
No, it's dangerous to move at night.
不，在晚上移動太危險了
Let's leave the car here and walk there tomorrow.
我們把車留在這裡，明天走過去看看
Okay.
好
So, are you…
所以，妳…
Ohma? Was that it?
是歐瑪，對吧？
Don't you want to play with the others?
妳不想跟其他人玩嗎？
I…
我…
I'll just annoy them.
我只會惹惱他們
Ouch.
好痛
So painful!
好痛喔
I can't bear it. Stop it.
我受不了了，停下來
Wait! Stop!
等等，住手
Wait, stop it, stop it! Stop!
等等，住手…住手
Sounded like you had a nightmare.
聽起來妳做惡夢了
Why are you in here?
你怎麼會在這裡？
Are you sick?
你生病了嗎？
There's nothing wrong with my body,
我的身體沒有問題
but I seem to have synchronized up with Tokio.
但我似乎與時男同步了
So is Tokio sick, then?
所以時男生病了？
No, no. Tokio is fine.
不是啦，沒有，時男沒事
It's just me who can't seem to get up.
似乎只有我起不來
Well, I guess it's good you're both okay then.
那麼，幸好你們兩個都沒事
Why are you here?
妳來這裡做什麼？
I…
我…
Do you know Ohma?
你認識歐瑪嗎？
Yeah, the one with the black glasses?
戴黑框眼鏡那個？
Yes, that one.
對，就是她
When I looked directly into Ohma's eyes, it made me hallucinate.
當我直視歐瑪的眼睛時，我會出現幻覺
I don't know how to say it. It was like my worst fears became real.
我不知道該如何形容 就像是我最可怕的惡夢成真了一樣
I mean, it was only a hallucination,
是說，也只是個幻覺啦
but sharp objects like blades and other things
但不知為何，我真的很害怕
seem to really scare me, for some reason.
刀子這類尖銳的物品
It's not like I have a scary memory of anything involving things like that.
倒不是我有過與尖銳物品相關的可怕回憶
I understand. It's a phobia.
我懂，那是一種恐懼症
I'm really scared of being trapped in small spaces.
我很害怕被困在狹小的空間裡
If I had a hallucination like that, I think I would faint.
如果我出現這類的幻覺，我想我會昏倒
I…
我…
Quite often I see things that others don't.
很常看到別人看不到的東西
Like what?
像是什麼？
Like…
像是…
I see figures floating in the sky,
我會見到有人物漂浮在空中
or I see something that's about to happen, before it does.
或者在事情尚未發生之前 見到即將發生的事
But it's a little vague.
但那有點模糊
And I'm not sure when what I see will happen.
而且我不確定我見到的事情何時會發生
It might feel like it'll happen tomorrow, but then it never does.
我感覺好像明天就會發生 但卻從來沒有發生
Or like it'll happen way in the future, but then it happens ten seconds later.
或者我感覺很久以後才會發生 但卻在十秒鐘之後就發生了
I-It's happening now.
現在…正在發生…
I see.
我知道了
So it's like a premonition, or an intuition of the future.
所以，這就像是對未來的預感 或是一種直覺
Everyone probably gets those feelings to a certain degree,
每個人可能或多或少都有過這種感覺
but it seems like yours are much stronger.
但妳的似乎特別強烈
Go away, go away.
走開，走開
I'm gonna go back to my room.
我要回我的房間了
Okay, rest up.
好的，好好休息
Ohma?
歐瑪？
-Why are you out here at this time? -Here.
-這種時間妳怎麼會在這裡？ -這個
You were waiting this whole time just to return my handkerchief?
妳為了把手帕還給我 在這裡一直等到現在？
Yes.
對
Mimihime, I'm…
彌美姬，我…
I'm sorry.
對不起
Don't do that!
不行
Go away, go away.
走開，走開
Go away.
走開
See? I'm fine.
看吧？我沒事
The thing that annoys everyone else has no effect on me.
這件事會惹惱其他人，但對我起不了作用
So you don't need to cry or apologize anymore.
所以妳再也不需要哭泣或是對我道歉了
What a mess.
一團亂
There's barely any space left to walk.
連走路的空間都不剩
My head's a total mess too.
我的思緒也是一團糟
That's the correct one. Please continue.
那個是正確的，請繼續
Plug C23 into Y7, and…
請將C23插入Y7，然後…
-What exactly are we building? -…F18 into Z11.
-我們到底在蓋什麼？ -將F18插入Z11
If the head of the Tech Department doesn't know, no one does.
如果連技術部主管都不知道 還有誰會知道？
No, I don't just mean these machines.
不，我指的不只是這些機器
I know the goal is to create a pure Heaven in a broken world.
我知道目標是要在 崩壞的世界裡創造一個純粹的天國
That much is clear.
這一點我很清楚
But beyond that,
但除此之外…
after the main goal of creating Heaven,
在知道主要目標是創造天國之後
the information we're being given is too fragmented.
所得到的資訊都太片斷了
After that, aren't we going to expand Heaven into the outside?
在那之後，我們不需要 把天國擴展到外面嗎？
That plan seems pretty clear to me.
我覺得那項計畫是理所當然的
Plus, Director said "soon," so it must be true.
況且，園長說過「就快了」 所以那一定是真的
I guess so.
我想是吧
Plus, we've already crossed so many taboos.
況且，我們已經觸碰了太多禁忌
Please continue with the task.
請繼續工作
B44 into A16.
將B44插入A16
H5 into Q31.
將H5插入Q31
God is telling us to go!
上帝正在督促我們這麼做
Let's execute the plan.
我們動手吧
Now's our chance, while the director isn't here.
園長不在，我們的機會來了
I've made the preliminary arrangements.
我完成了初步安排
Then when can we start? Specifically?
我們究竟何時可以開始？
If the gate to the outside were to accidentally open, then anytime.
如果通往外面的大門不小心開啟的話 隨時可以開始
I wouldn't call that specific.
這樣不夠具體
-Oops. It's time for the milk. -What?
-糟了，餵奶的時間到了 -什麼？
-Please excuse me. -Wait, Dr. Sawatari!
-我得先走了 -等等，猿渡醫生
Hey, wait!
等等
Good morning, everyone.
大家早
Today is Saturday, July 20th. Ten'ei 18.
今天是天永18年7月20日，星期六
For first period, please gather at the pool.
請在第一節課到泳池集合
There will be no swimming, so you may attend in your uniforms.
不需要游泳，所以請穿制服出席
-Want to compete today? -Yeah, sounds good.
-今天要比一場嗎？ -好啊
Why are you in your swimsuit?
妳為什麼穿泳裝？
I guess some people didn't listen properly and came in their swimsuits.
我想有些人沒有注意聽，所以穿泳裝來了
Right, Anzu?
對吧，杏？
Don't fall in.
別掉進去了
Mimihime.
彌美姬
It's Tokio!
是時男
Tokio.
時男
You look fine!
太好了，你看起來很健康
Your hair got longer.
你的頭髮變長了
They said I can come back to school soon.
他們說我很快就能回去上課
Really?
真的嗎？
-We can play with Tokio again! -That's great!
-我們又可以跟時男玩了 -太好了
Okay, everyone,
各位
please stop talking and give me your full attention.
請別再聊天，注意聽我說
What? What lesson is that?
什麼？這是什麼課程啊？
All the students are gathered together.
學生全都集合了
Is it a school assembly?
是學校集會嗎？
We will be having a test shortly.
我們馬上要進行測驗
It will be a long test, but you will have plenty of time.
這個測驗很長，但你們會有足夠的時間
-A test? -What kind of test?
-測驗？ -什麼樣的測驗？
When you are lost and cannot find the answer,
當你感到迷惘，找不到答案時
please proceed in the direction that you believe to be the correct one.
請朝你認為正確的方向前進
To reach the outside of the outside
你們要以蛭子的角色
is your role, as Hiruko.
抵達外面的外面
The first problem will appear momentarily.
第一個問題隨時會出現
I wish you all the best of luck.
祝各位一切順利
That was some weird lesson.
好奇怪的課程喔
Anzu, let's go for a swim!
杏，我們去游泳吧
I think I'll pass.
我就不去了
Hey, Taka.
鷹
What is it?
怎麼了？
What do you think the test is?
你覺得會是什麼樣的測驗？
It's sudden, but they did give us notice. At least it's not totally out of the blue.
來得很突然，但他們的確通知了我們 不至於太晴天霹靂
I'm not sure why, but I'm worried.
不知為什麼，我很擔心
Anzu, you're smart. You'll be fine!
杏，妳很聰明，妳會沒事的啦
It should be me who's worried.
該擔心的人是我吧
That's not really what I meant.
我不是那個意思
Did you hear? They mentioned Hiruko.
你聽到了嗎？他們提到了蛭子
Did they?
是嗎？
I felt like I was being called by my real name.
感覺他們好像叫了我的真名
One that I had completely forgotten.
一個被我遺忘了的真名
Me too.
我也是
I had the same feeling.
我也有這種感覺
TOKIO JR. - JR. C
（小時男，JR.C）
Sleep tight.
睡個好覺喔
I thought you were studying, but it's a game isn't it?
我以為妳在念書，但妳在玩遊戲，對吧？
What's the point of studying if we don't know what the test is about?
我們根本不知道測驗的內容 念書有什麼用？
Yeah, good point.
對呀，說的也是
THE TEST BEGINS
（測驗開始）